<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ's ministers must shortly put off their tabernacles set forth in a funeral sermon preach'd at Hungerford at the interring of Mr. Ric. Moor, late minister of the Gospel there / by Samuel Tomlyns ...</title>
            <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1857A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32812</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12761921</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12761921</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93518</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62904)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93518)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1537:49)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ's ministers must shortly put off their tabernacles set forth in a funeral sermon preach'd at Hungerford at the interring of Mr. Ric. Moor, late minister of the Gospel there / by Samuel Tomlyns ...</title>
                  <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London:</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and torn, with print showthrough and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93518:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93518:1"/>
            <p>Chriſt's Miniſters muſt ſhortly put off their TABERNACLES.</p>
            <p>Set forth in a Funeral Sermon: Preach'd at <hi>Hungerford,</hi> at the Interring OF <hi>Mr. Ric. Moor,</hi> Late Miniſter of the Goſpel there.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Tomlyns,</hi> M. A. and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Marlborough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Threee Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93518:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93518:2"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory, TO The Honourable Sir <hi>HEALE HOOK,</hi> Baronet, of <hi>Chilton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Wilts;</hi> Grace, Mercy, and Peace be multiplied, from God the Father, and from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>THE Sermon that I preach'd at the Funeral of my Worthy Friend, and your near Neighbour, Mr. <hi>Richard Moor,</hi> late of <hi>Hungerford,</hi> I here preſent to you, with ſome ſmall Enlargements. I did not think of publiſhing it, but the importunity of ſome hath prevailed with me to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe and print it. The Subject inſiſted on, is weighty; it treats of <hi>putting off our Earthly Tabernacles.</hi> It is that which muſt certainly be, and it can be done but once; <hi>It is appointed for all men once to die,</hi> Heb. <hi>9.27.</hi> and it is ſaid, <hi>The Maſter of the Houſe will once Riſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:93518:3"/>ſhut the Door of his Houſe,</hi> Luke <hi>13.25.</hi> He will riſe to ſhut it againſt the ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Negligent, against the impenitent and unbelieving. And when he is once Riſen, and hath ſhut the door, he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver riſe again to open it. Thoſe that are once excluded are excluded, and undone for ever. The Errors committed in this Life cannot be redreſſed or mended, by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving again; and Christ will never revoke his Sentence that he hath pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that have trifled away their day of Life, and ſinned away their day of Grace; it is your Duty and Intereſt to think of and prepare for the putting off your Earthly Tabernacle. If a man be warned out of one Houſe in this World, he will conſider how to furniſh, and provide himſelf with another. Our Souls must diſlodge out of theſe Cottages of Clay, and Tabernacles of Fleſh; and ſhall we not think of another habitation? How will God diſpoſe of us, where will he ſix us for Eternity? Then we begin to be wiſe, when we number our days, and think of, and prepare for our Removal into an Everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting State;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19.</note> then we establiſh our hearts, when we <hi>caſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor
<pb facs="tcp:93518:3"/>within the Vail;</hi> then we provide never-failing Springs of Conſolation, when we look not at the things that <hi>are ſeen, but at the things that are not ſeen, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>4.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How unreaſonable is it for an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Soul to mind only its Tabernacle-state in this World, and to put all its Comforts and Happineſs upon an inch, a moment of time, and on days of an hands breadth? Would it not be Folly and Madneſs for a man to be careful how he ſhould live for one day, and be careleſs of all his other days? And is it not worſe to be ſolicitous for the one ſhort day of Time, and to be regardleſs of the innumerable days of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity? O why ſhould we be ſo dim, ſo ſhort ſighted, as to diſcern only the Objects of Senſe, and things near to us, and not to behold things that are afar off; the Feast that is to be enjoyed, the Treaſure that is to be poſſeſſed, the Country that is to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited after death. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of it as bad for perſons to be born into the world, and have nothing; to be Heirs of Poverty and Beggery, <hi>Eccleſ. 5.14. He begetteth a Son, and there is nothing in his hand:</hi> But it is much worſe to be born into Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb facs="tcp:93518:4"/>and to have nothing; to have inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in no Friend, Title to no Inheritance, Claim to no ſuitable, and ſatisfying Good, to live on for Eternity; for nothing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main but the ſin of men, and the wrath of God, <hi>1. John</hi> last, <hi>3. John</hi> laſt. By the Fall of the First <hi>Adam</hi> we were all capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated to ſeen things, and fell under the power of the Life of Senſe. It is the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and rich Grace of God that muſt raiſe us from this low and baſe life of Senſe, to an higher and Nobler life of Faith; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with, and dwell on inviſible and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal things in our thoughts and affections, tho <hi>we have all ſinned, and ſo come ſhort of the Glory of God, Rom. 3.23.</hi> Yet it is poſſible we may be juſtified by Faith, have peace with God, and rejoyce in the hope of the Glory of God. The Son of God hath proclaimed a <hi>Spiritual Jubilee,</hi> Iſa. <hi>61.2.</hi> that not only our loſt liberty may be retrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but alſo our alienated Inheritance may be recovered. The Lord fix your Eye and center your Heart on inviſible and eternal things that when you ſhall be a Steward out of Office, you may be an Heir in poſſeſſion. Theſe are the unfeigned deſires of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Affectionate and Humble Servant, <hi>S. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93518:4"/>
            <head>A Funeral Sermon, Preached at <hi>Hungerford</hi> at the Interring of Mr. <hi>Richard Moor,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel there.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Pet. 1.14.</hi>
                  </bibl> Knowing that ſhortly I muſt put off this my Tabernacle, even as our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath ſhewed me.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the Text we may obſerve theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Parts, a Name given to the <hi>Body,</hi> it is call'd a <hi>Tabernacle;</hi> and this Name imports its frailty and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; there is a vaſt difference between the preſent and future Eſtate of it; now it is a Feeble Tabernacle, but hereafter it ſhall be a ſtrong and everlaſting <hi>Houſe,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. In this we groan, earneſtly deſiring to be cloathed with our houſes which ſhall be Raiſed by the ſecond ſinleſs <hi>Adam,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>; or this Name implies that Men continue in this <hi>Tabernacle</hi> but a little time, while they are Warring with Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies below, and Travelling to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe above.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We have a deſcription of Death; it is the putting off this <hi>Tabernacle;</hi> we are but
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93518:5"/>
               <hi>Temporary Sojourners</hi> in the Body; by ſin our firſt Parents Sold the Fee-ſimple of life, and we have now but a ſhort Leaſe of it, yea, are Tenants at the will of our great Landlord, when he removes us out of our <hi>Tabernacle</hi> we muſt depart and be gone; that Body which to ſtanding <hi>Adam</hi> would have been an everlaſting Houſe, to Fallen Man, is but a Temporary Cottage; but this expreſſion of the Apoſtle, <hi>to put off this Tabernacle,</hi> may ſeem a Catachriſis, or bold Metaphor; yet if we ſtop not in the ſurface, but ſearch deeper into the Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, we ſhall find great Emphaſis, and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy in it. A <hi>Tabernacle</hi> is a ſtanding Garment, and a Garment is a movable <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi> they both ſerve for the ſame end and uſe, to keep off the inconvenience or hurt the Body may ſuſtain by being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the open Air, to Rainy, or cold Weather.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> intimates, that the time for his departure out of the Body was app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ning, and near at hand, <hi>I muſt ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put off this Tabernacle.</hi> If Violent hands do pull down this <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> it will be ſhortly put off; if it be ſuffered to continue till it fall of it ſelf, that then it will be ſhortly put off, this Clay Cottage will ſoon moulder down, this Lamp of Life will quickly go out, if no violent ſtrong breath
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93518:5"/>doth blow it out, we ſhall of our own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord within a little time, drop from the Tree of Life, if no violent Wind doth ſhake us down, or cruel hand doth a little ſooner pluck us from it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us his eſpecial ground why he did know <hi>that ſhortly he muſt put off his Earthly Tabernacle,</hi> becauſe the Lord Jeſus Chriſt had told him ſo; Jeſus Chriſt could not be miſtaken about a future Event. He knew what Cruel Men would endeavour to commit, and what he himſelf would permit, and therefore certainly warned <hi>Peter</hi> of that violent Death that did abide him. <hi>Peter</hi> in theſe words ſeems to relate to, and reflect on what is Recorded in the 21 <hi>John</hi> 18, 19. <hi>That when he was old another ſhould Gird him, that is, with Bonds of Chains, and carry him whither he would not;</hi> that is, he ſhould be led to ſuch Hard Sufferings, and cruel Death as Nature was averſe to, and did recoil from. <hi>Peter</hi> had lived ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years ſince this <hi>Prediction,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fulfilling and accompliſhing of it, could not now be far off.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine that the words offer, and offer'd to us is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctr. Chriſt's Miniſters muſt ſhortly put off their Earthly Tabernacles. Peter</hi> an Eminent Apoſtle was to ſubmit to, and fall under the Fatal Stroke of Death: To Die in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93518:6"/>is common to all Men, but to be put to Death for the Goſpel, this is peculiar to <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Saints.</hi> Death makes War againſt the <hi>Ambaſſadours</hi> of Peace, blows out the Sacred Lamps of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the very Friends of the <hi>Bridegroom;</hi> ſo that they can no more Sollicit a Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age between the Lord of Life, and poor Periſhing Sinners. This King of Terrors not only Executes Saints, but alſo cuts off even Chriſts Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es-men, and ſows them in the Duſt, Reapes the Lords Harveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Removes them into the Barn of Heaven, and gathers them into the Garners of Glory; that ſad Providence that is the occaſion of this <hi>Solemnity,</hi> is an evident Proof, and clear demonſtration of the Truth of the Doctrine, one of the Lords Meſſengers in the Flower, and Prime of his Days, hath quickly put off his <hi>Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of the Doctrine I ſhall 1. Take notice of the Name given to the Body, 2. Inſiſt upon the Name given to Death. 3. I ſhall ſhew you why even Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters muſt put off this <hi>Tabernacle.</hi> 4. I ſhall evidence what ground they have to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>that ſhortly they must put off their Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us conſider the Name put on the Body, It is called a <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> as I hinted before.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93518:6"/>
            <p n="1">1. To expreſs its weakneſs; on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it is Styled an Earthen Veſſel, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. By a little knock this Earthly Veſſel may eaſily be daſh'd to Pieces, a little Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs looſes the Cords, pulls up the Stakes, and overthrows this <hi>Tabernacle.</hi> A Diſeaſe of a few days pulls it down to the duſt, as graſs we ſpring up and wither, as bubble we riſe and fall, as vapours we appear and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away, 4. <hi>James</hi> 14.14. <hi>Job</hi> 1. We act a ſhort part on the Stage of Time, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire within the Curtains of Eternity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is called a <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> to Note the ſhort continuance of the Soul in it; it muſt ſoon diſlodg, and remove to another Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation. The Traveller had his Tent; ſo <hi>Jacob</hi> when he journied towards <hi>Canaan,</hi> he pitch'd his Tent in <hi>Mount Gilead, Gen.</hi> 31.25. And Soldiers when they Camped in the open Field they had their Tents, 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 11.11. When <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> did Beſiege <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah,</hi> they did abide in Tents. The word <hi>Tent</hi> and <hi>Tabernacle</hi> are uſed promiſcuouſly for the ſame thing, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.1. <hi>David</hi> is ſaid to pitch a Tent for the <hi>Ark of God,</hi> but in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.17. it is ſaid, <hi>they brought the Ark of God, and ſet it in its place, in the midſt of the Tabernacle that David had pitched for it:</hi> For this Reaſon the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> are ſaid to <hi>dwell in Tabernacles, or to ſojourn in Tents,</hi> Heb. 11.9. <hi>to ſhew that they had no long time to ſtay in this World;</hi> that they accounted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93518:7"/>to be but <hi>Pilgrims and Strangers on Earth,</hi> Heb. 11.13. that they look for an <hi>abiding City, that they deſired a Country above, Heb.</hi> 11. and were Travelling towards an <hi>inviſible</hi> and <hi>glorious World,</hi> our welfare will ſoon be accompliſhed, and then the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <hi>Tent</hi> is taken down our <hi>Pilgrimage</hi> will quickly be at an end, and then the <hi>Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers Tent</hi> ceaſes, and is gone; Saints not only have no abiding City in this World, but they would have none, they deſire none below.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Death is here called, <hi>the putting off this Tabernacle;</hi> this Phraſe may inſtruct us, and teach us three conſiderable Leſſons, and weighty truths, 1. The Nobility and Excellency of the Soul, the Body is but a Tabernacle, the Soul is the Tenant, and Inhabitant in it; how much better is the Tenant, than the Tabernacle, therefore Souls ſhould be moſt highly valued, chiefly thought of, cared for, and attended to the Soul doth not follow the ſtate of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but the Body follows the ſtate of the Soul, either for a bleſſed or a miſerable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity: Will a man lay out all his Time, and waſte his Eſtate to beautify, flouriſh, and fine out his Houſe, and will he neglect, famiſh and Starve himſelf? And that we feed, heal, cloath our Bodies, but for get all the concerns, wants and neceſſities of our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93518:7"/>Souls, and that we doat on our baſer, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, forget, and famiſh our better part.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This expreſſion of <hi>putting off our Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernatle,</hi> may teach us the immortality of our Souls; the Body is but the Tent of the Soul, a Traveller, or Soldier hath no ſuch dependance on his Tent, but he can go out of it, and yet live, there is no ſuch neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary connexion between the Tent and the Traveller, but he can exiſt and ſubſiſt, tho his Tent be taken down. <hi>Ariſtotle, de anima,</hi> tho a Heathen, did acknowledg that the Soul came, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from without; by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion he ſeems to intimate that the Soul is of a higher Original, of a more Noble Extraction, than to derive its Pedigree from Progenitors below: Man is ſo great and noble a Creature, that he came from two Worlds, and therefore muſt needs be for two Worlds; our Fleſh was propagar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Parents below, but our Spirits de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, and derive our Original from a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther above, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. This lower world is but a paſſage for Travelling. Souls to journey through, but the upper world is the home and reſt for Holy and Bleſſed Souls to dwell in; the Body is but the Garment of the Soul, as a man can live, tho he put off his Cloaths, ſo the Soul can continue its being, tho it be ſtript of the Garment of the Fleſh; a naked diveſted Spirit can live
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93518:8"/>in the World of Spirits, tho it leave the World of Bodies. Death in Scripture is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten called a <hi>Sleep,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.10. <hi>Job</hi> 7.21. this Phraſe is uſed only concerning Men, nor concerning <hi>Beaſts, Plants,</hi> or <hi>Trees,</hi> theſe Creatures have a Senſitive, or Vegetative Life; but when they die, they are not ſaid to ſleep, becauſe their Life is utterly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, and totally aboliſhed; but when Men Die, they do but <hi>Sleep;</hi> the Senſes of the Body are indeed ſeal'd up, it becomes a Carcaſe without Senſe or Motion, but the Soul is alive, the Light is ſnatched out of the Lanthorn of the Body, but is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringuiſhed; Life is ſtill preſerved in the Soul as the root; and tho men ſleep yet there is one that will a wake them; Chriſt the firſt born of Gods new Family is up fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, he is raiſed out of the Grave, and will call out, and rouſe up all his Spiritual Brethren and Siſters, out of the long ſleep of Death.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Peters</hi> ſaying, <hi>He muſt put off his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi> doth further mind us of, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us in a great Duty, that Saints ought to Die in obedience, and willingly to lay down the body; tho Chriſtians are ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a violent death, and cut off by cruel hands; tho their fleſhly Garment be pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed off, and their <hi>Earthly Tabernacle</hi> by bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Enemies be plucked down; yet God expects, and Chriſt looks for ſubmiſſion to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93518:8"/>the fatal Stroke; and that we ſhould chooſe Sufferings, and Death, rather than ſin; this is to put off our <hi>Tabernacle:</hi> when God takes away the Souls of Hypocrites, <hi>Job.</hi> 27.8. we muſt commit them into his Hands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.5. when others are driven away out of the World, <hi>Prov.</hi> 32. we muſt deſire to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and to be with Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 23. <hi>We muſt die to the Lord, Rom.</hi> 14.8. that is, we muſt breath out our Souls, and give them up when he calls for them, and requires them; we muſt die in compliance with his will, to be more ſubject to him, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more poſſeſſed by him, to enjoy a Peace; and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Communication with him; not ſo much to be freed of <hi>Sufferings,</hi> as to be rid of <hi>Sin:</hi> To be perfected in the Image and Life of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Why muſt Chriſts Miniſters, as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, put off their Tabarnacles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. They have contracted, and are involved in guilt, <hi>all have ſinned, Rom.</hi> 3.23. As they are not free from the Contagion of Iniquity, ſo they are not exempted from the Sentence of Death, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19. Sin dwells in them, and this opens the door, and lets in Death upon them; they as well as other Chriſtians do want the Soader, the Glew, the Cement of a perfect inherent Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and therefore their Building doth moulder, and the Stones of it ſall one from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93518:9"/>another; Death is compar'd to a Flood, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.5. <hi>Thou carriest them away as with a Flood,</hi> this Flood is very general, it carrie; away High and Low, Rich and Poor, Saints and Sinners; we read but of two little Iſlands, <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> that have not hitherto been over whelm'd with this Flood, all the reſt of Mankind ſhall be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with this Plood, except thoſe that ſhall be found a live at the laſt day. It is appointed for all men once to die, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. This is a Law not to be Repealed, a <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> not to be Reverſed, the Body is Dead by Reaſon of Sin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10. Death paſſeth over all men, becauſe all have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Miniſters muſt die, that ſometimes by their Death they may Eminently Glorify God; Chriſt foretold <hi>Peters</hi> Martyrdom, and by his being girded, and led whither he would not did ſignify that violent death whereby he ſhould Glorify God, and <hi>John</hi> 1.18, 19. that he durſt not lay down his Liſe, that is moſt ſweet, and ſubmit to Death that is moſt bitter to Nature, in obedience to an inviſible God, and in hope of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen World; this ſignally Glorifies God, and benefits his People. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of his being offered on the Service and Sacrifice of the <hi>Philippians</hi> Faith, 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the word ſignifies a Drink-offering;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93518:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Drink-offering uſed to be annexed to the Sacrifices, and theſe were of Wines. On this account the Vine in the Parable ſaith, <hi>That by its Wine it cheared the Heart of God,</hi> Judg. 9. <hi>as well as of men;</hi> the Apoſtle with alluſion to the Sacrifices of the Law, was willing that his Blood ſhould be poured out by cruel hands, that God might diſpoſe his true Offerings to this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Gracious end, to promote and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Faith of the <hi>Philippians;</hi> the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Paſtors</hi> for the true Religion do ſo greatly tend to Edify their Flocks, and to ſtrengthen their Belief of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. <hi>Paul</hi> would not have Died for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain Doctrine, or for a Fable invented by men; he was fully perſwaded of the truth of the Goſpel of Chriſt, that he durſt to venture his Life, his Soul, his all for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity on the credit of this Doctrine; ſo Chriſt was Magnified by him, <hi>and Saints were confirmed, and eſtabliſhed by his ſufferings,</hi> Phil. 1.12, 13, 20.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Chriſts Miniſters do put off their Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi> to ſhew that God is not ſtinted, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to particular Miniſters; he can bare up his Name, ſupport his Kingdom, carry on his Intereſt, tho he cut off <hi>eminent Emba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſadors,</hi> and gives a quiet reſt to painful La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers; God hath abſolute need of no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if he cut off ſome, he can raiſe up o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93518:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>if the day and work of ſome be done, he hath a reſidue of the Spirit, and can fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, fit, and thruſt out other Labourers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Harveſt; if Pillars be pulled away, yet the Church, that is the Temple of the <hi>Living God,</hi> ſhall not fall; God hath others to ſubſtitute in the room of thoſe that are ſnatched away, as God reneweth the Face of the Earth by ſending forth his Spirit, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.30. tho Plants and Trees decay, Birds die, Beaſts periſh, Men give up the Ghoſt, yet Gods great Farm is not unſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his Houſe unfurniſhed, or deſtitute of Inhabitants; ſo, tho Saints die, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are ſnatch'd away, yet God ſends forth his <hi>Spirit,</hi> and begets a <hi>new Generation</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> and raiſes up a <hi>new Stock,</hi> and <hi>ſuptly of Miniſters,</hi> and ſo, renews the <hi>Face of the Church.</hi> God will not want Friends to wooe for that <hi>Bridegroom,</hi> Ambaſſadours of Chriſt for Peace, Heralds to Proclaim Chriſt <hi>the King of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. God calls his Miniſters home, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Reward of their <hi>Labours, to reap the fruits of all their pains,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.7, 8. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith. <hi>That after Death there remnined for him a Crown of Righteouſneſs,</hi> God deſign'd it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, God laid it up for him; Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters go hence to ſet on the Throne, to wear the Crown, to poſſeſs the Eternal Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to partake of the everlaſting Feaſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93518:10"/>promiſed to them; when God ſaith to the Body, <hi>Return to thy dust,</hi> Gen. 3.19. then he ſpeaks to the Soul, as God did to <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 31.3. <hi>Return to the Land of thy Fathers, and to thy Kindred, and I will be with thee;</hi> when the Soul is turned out of an <hi>Earthly Tabernacle,</hi> it is taken into an <hi>Heavenly Houſe,</hi> when the Fleſh is Sown in the duſt, the Spirit reaps up the Fruit of its Faith, in a ſtate of Glory.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Ministers put off their Tabernacle,</hi> becauſe the Lord intends to Glorify himſelf, by raiſing them, and the Bodies of all his <hi>Saints</hi> again, tho they ſleep and have a long dark Night in the Grave, yet a bright and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable morning will come, <hi>Pſal</hi> 49.14. tho they put off the Garment of the Body, yet Jeſus will dreſs them, and put on theſe Cloaths again; tho they go out of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as a Tabernacle, yet they ſhall return to them again, and dwell in them as a houſe for ever, theſe their <hi>vile bodies ſhall be chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and made like the glorious Body of Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3.21. <hi>The bodies of Saints are but ſowed in the Earth,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.42, 43, 44 they muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear and Spring up again to everlaſting life. Jeſus Chriſt is a <hi>Second Adam and an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Father,</hi> Iſa 8.6. He muſt therefore beget the Bodies of his People from the Dead: <hi>They muſt bare the Image of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Adam,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.48, 49. old <hi>Adams</hi> Holding and Tenute muſt ceaſe, and be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93518:11"/>extinguiſhed, and we muſt be <hi>Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in our Bodies,</hi> as well <hi>as in our Souls,</hi> and then we ſhall hold them from Jeſus Chriſt; our Bodies are now as knocked, bruiſed, or broken Veſſels, that are caſt into the Furnace, that they may be melted, and new moulded, and framed, as the <hi>Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> was taken down in the Wilderneſs, but was ſet up again in <hi>Canaan;</hi> ſo tho the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle</hi> of the body be diſſolved, and taken to pieces in the Wilderneſs of this World, yet it ſhall be joyn'd together, and ſet up for ever in the Heavenly <hi>Canaan:</hi> thoſe that dwell in this <hi>Tabernacle</hi> do <hi>groan,</hi> being <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened:</hi> but thoſe that dwell in the Body, as a <hi>Houſe built by the hand of the Lord ſtretched out from Heaven,</hi> ſhall <hi>Sing, Rejoyce,</hi> and <hi>Triumph for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Miniſters have ground to conclude, <hi>that ſhortly they muſt put off their Tabernacles,</hi> tho we cannot ſay as <hi>Peter, That we have a particular Revelation from Chriſt, of the Kind, or Time of our Death,</hi> yet we may ſay, <hi>that our God hath ſhewed us that it muſt be ſhortly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Gods Threatning doth evidence it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Duſt we are, and to duſt we muſt return;</hi> what God ſaid to the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats, and ſaith over to his Children, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn ye Sons of Men,</hi> Pſal. 90.3. when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires us to return, we cannot ſtay here, but muſt be gone. <hi>God will change our Countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93518:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſend us away, Job</hi> 14.20. we know not how ſoon, how ſuddenly God may ſpeak this word, <hi>return ye Sons of Men:</hi> we cannot foreſee when that Wind of Sickneſs or other accident will ariſe, that will blaſt our Flower, and blow out our Lamp of Life, Death ſometimes lays in <hi>Ambuſhment</hi> and break forth unexpectedly on perſons.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Death of other Servants, and Meſſengers of God, that daily are called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and drop into the Grave before our Eyes, doth ſhew us that ſhortly we muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them into the duſt, <hi>Zeck.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, where are they; and the Prophets, do they live for ever?</hi> Thoſe holy Men, that were inſpired by the Spirit, were yet mowed down by the Syth of death. Many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Famous Miniſters have taken the Grave for their Houſe, and have made their Bed in Darkneſs. And muſt not we travel in the ſame Road, and take the way of all the Earth? Will not our Glaſs be quickly run, our Sun ſet, and the Thread of our Lives be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> cut?</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Diſtempers that we feel, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities that exerciſe us, the Diſeaſes we groan under, do ſenſibly teach us, <hi>That ſhortly we muſt put off our Tabernacles;</hi> All Pains and Diſtempers are Deaths working in us, and warring againſt us. Theſe are the Harbingers of the <hi>King of Terrors,</hi> that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93518:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>come to take up Quarters and Lodgings for Death in our Earthly Tabernacles: All the painful Maladies thou doſt complain of, are Deaths Batteries againſt the Fort of the body, are ſtroaks towards the Felling of the Tree; are Warnings to remove out of <hi>this Earthly Tabernacle;</hi> as <hi>one Poſt, one Meſſenger,</hi> ſhould go after another, to inform the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that his City was taken at one end, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.31. So the decays of our ſtrength, of our ſight, of our hearing, of our taſte, doth plainly tell us, that <hi>Death hath taken us at one end.</hi> This <hi>King of Terrors</hi> is lodged already at the <hi>Cinque-Ports</hi> of our Senſes, with a deſign to conquer the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of our bodies.</p>
            <p>The only uſe that I ſhall make of this Doctrine, is an Uſe of <hi>Exhortation.</hi> And here</p>
            <p n="1">1. I would humbly direct, and earneſtly preſs a word of <hi>Exhortation</hi> on you my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Brethren in the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> that are here preſent; Muſt we that are the <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> and <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> of Chriſt <hi>ſhortly put off our Tabernacles?</hi> O then le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll improve our ſhort time, beſtir and put forth our ſelves to the utmoſt, while our day laſts, and our ſtrength continues; it is better for a Knife to wear away by continual uſe, than to ruſt away by diſuſe; why doth God ſhine into our <hi>Hearts,</hi> but that we ſhould ſet forth, and impart the <hi>light of the knowledg
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93518:12"/>of the Glory of God in the Face of Chriſt to others,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.6. what will it avail us if we be large ponds our ſelves to hold much water, if we are not ſpiritual pipes to convey the water of Life to thirſty and periſhing Souls, as the Bread that Chriſt did break to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute to others, <hi>was multiplied, and did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in his hands,</hi> Matt. 14.19, 20. ſo while we divide the <hi>word of Truth,</hi> and <hi>break the Bread of Life to others,</hi> our own knowledg in the <hi>Myſtery of Chriſt</hi> will increaſe, and our own <hi>Spiritual Life</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> will be improved. O ſtrive to break hard Hearts with the hammer of the word, and to cut off the Members of the old Man with the <hi>ſword of the Spirit:</hi> labour to awaken ſleepy drowſy Sinners, to reduce thoſe that are gone aſtray, to ſput ſluggiſh and loytering Souls, pluck brands out of the Fire, ſnatch the prey from the paw and mouth of the roaring Lion; Chriſt bids his Diſciples to <hi>go to their loſt ſheep of the Houſe of Iſrael,</hi> Matt. 10.6. Chriſt awakens their pity, ſtirs their bowels, draweth forth their him paſſions by the name he gives to poor ſinners, <hi>they are loſt ſheep, periſhing ſheep,</hi> ſuch a are ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Hell, dropping into the Bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit, and will you not beſtir your ſelves to ſtep, reſcue and ſave them? O let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, the danger, the diſtreſs, the neceſſities of Souls, and be inſtant, urgent,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93518:13"/>preſſing upon them in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon; let us ſound the Trumpet, and brandiſh the flaming Sword of Gods threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, to alarm and rouſe up ſullen and preſumptuous ſinners. Let us ſhoot the keen and ſharp Arrows of the word to wound the Hearts of the workers of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that they may fall down as a Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſubmitting People under Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. yet let me beſeech you to Sollicit Heaven, that the Hand of Chriſt may be on your Hearts and Hands, as the Hand of the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> was on the Hand of the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> when he did draw the Bow to ſhoot, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.16, 17. If Chriſts hands be not on our hands, when we draw the Spiritual Bow, we ſhall neither ſhoot far, or hit right, or wound deeply; when we have affected, and wounded the hearts of thoſe that were ſecure, let us diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play the banner of Chriſts Love, to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage drooping, diſponding and ſinking Souls: Let us bind up the broken hearted, and comfort the <hi>Mourners.</hi> Brethren, our work is great and difficult; it is no eaſy matter to level Mountains of <hi>Carnal Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Iſa.</hi> 40.4. and then to fill, and lift up Valleys; to chear, relieve and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage <hi>Doubting, Dejected, Deſpairing Souls;</hi> the Lord muſt give us the Tongue of the Learned to ſpeak a word in due ſeaſon to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93518:13"/>him that is weary, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.40: Let us plead Chriſts cauſe with all our might, and let us attack and ſtorm Satans Kingdom with our utmoſt ſtrength. O that we might wound and cruſh the head of the old Serpent, and deſtroy his works, and build a Temple and Habitation for God through the Spirit. We may ſee <hi>Peter</hi> making this uſe of the Doctrine of Mortality, and thus to improve the thoughts of his approaching death, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12, 13. <hi>I will not be negligent to put you always in remembrance of theſe things.</hi> Yea I think it meet as long as I am in this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle to ſtir you up by putting you in remembrance. Though Death quenches Life, yet the thoughts of it quickens Chriſts Miniſters to their work; though the putting off their Tabernacles doth ſtop their Motions, and end their Labours, yet the clear apprehenſion, and daily conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this, doth enliven and haſten their ſpiritual Motions, and double their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in the work of Chriſt. <hi>John</hi> 9.4. <hi>I muſt work the Works of him that ſent me while it is day; the night cometh when none can work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I would ſpeak a word of <hi>Exhortation</hi> to you the Auditors that hear me this Day. <hi>Peter</hi> would put thoſe in remembrance to whom he did write; O give me leave to put you in remembrance of ſome great and weighty truths that may affect your hearts,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93518:14"/>and benefit your ſouls. I muſt ſhortly <hi>put off my Tabernacle;</hi> therefore I would earneſtly addreſs my ſelf to you about the weighty concernments of your Souls, and of <hi>Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let me mind you of your <hi>Reconciliation to God.</hi> We are Ambaſſadors for Chriſt; as tho God did beſeech you by us, we pray you in Chriſt's ſtead, to be reconciled to God, 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 5.20. Will you not dread <hi>the Enmity,</hi> and deſire <hi>the Favour and Friendſhip of an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Maiesty!</hi> O let not the breach be kept open, and the Enmity be kept up between God and your Souls. Will you not fear an Immortal Adverſary, and an Eternal An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? will you not tremble when the ſtorm of Vengeance hangs over your heads; the Ax of God is laid to your Root, his Arrows are levelled at your hearts. God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to us the <hi>Word of Reconciliation,</hi> and we muſt preſs and urge your <hi>Reconciliation to God.</hi> We are the Lord's Agents and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors. Is not this a wonderful Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention, that the King of Glory will ſend Ambaſſadors to his Subjects; that the God of Glory will ſend to his Creatures; an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite offended Majeſty will ſend firſt to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels and Enemies? Will you liſten to our Meſſage, and be reconciled to God? Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, God hath been at great coſt and charge, he hath made wonderful preparations to eſtabliſh peace; God's Anger could not be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93518:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>quenched, nor our Pardon written out in the Blood of his Son; Enmity could not be ſlain, except Chriſt were crucified; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie between God and us could not be buried but in the Grave of his Son; a City of Refuge could not be built for us, if the Temple of the Godhead were not pulled down to the ground, God's Sword could not be ſheathed, or ſleep towards us, if it did not firſt awake, ſmite and cut off his Son, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.7. The debt could not be remitted to us, if not firſt exacted of Chriſt; God hath delivered up his Son to the death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. that he might deliver us from <hi>the wrath to come,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. <hi>laſt.</hi> Hath God done ſo much, and acted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o far, that he might lay aſide his Righteous Enmity againſt us; and that we will not yet be perſwaded to lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide our wicked Enmity againſt him. 2. God hath no need of your Friendſhip, neither doth he fear your Enmity. 3. Your Enmity is moſt fooliſh; Shall Stubble challenge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming Fire? or <hi>Potters Veſſel dare to contend with a Rod of Iron?</hi> 4 Your Enmity is cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; God is <hi>the habitation of Justice,</hi> Jer. 50.47. but <hi>ſin dwells in us, Rom.</hi> 17. Our ways are perverſe but God cannot take a wrong ſtep, draw a crooked line, nor do an act of inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; his very ſtrength loves Righteouſneſs, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 99.4. <hi>God is love,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.8. but your <hi>arn al mind is enmity againſt God, Rom.</hi> 5.7. O
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93518:15"/>will you not be aſhamed; will you not be humbled that you have ſuch hard hearts, ſuch rebellious wills, that though God is willing to be reconciled by the Death of his Son, yet you are not willing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to him by the death of your Sins.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I would put you in remembrance of a Fountain that is opened, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.1. it is opened where we could never have thought of, imagined, or expected it did ever enter into the Heart of man, that God ſhould open a Fountain in the <hi>Pierced ſide,</hi> in the <hi>wounded heart of his own Son:</hi> that a Laver ſhould be provided, a Bath be made of the Blood of the <hi>Son of God;</hi> O will you neglect, will you deſpiſe the Fountain that God hath opened? the Blood of Chriſt hath ſuch an everlaſting Virtue, to purge Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, to cleanſe from ſin and unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that it may well be compared to a Fountain flowing, and never dry. Chriſt hath offered a Sacrifice of an Eternal virtue, and brought an everlaſting Righteouſneſs. O finners, will you not be convinced of your great need of this Fountain, is there not an unclean, corrupt, pernicious Fountain in you, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.7. <hi>As a Fountain caſts out its water, ſo Jeruſalem caſts out its Wickedneſs,</hi> God doth not ſpeak this of <hi>Babylon,</hi> of <hi>Memphis,</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus,</hi> but of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that profeſſed to be the Servants and Worſhippers of God. Do
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93518:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>not flatter thy ſelf, be not deceived, though thou art a <hi>Chriſtian by Name,</hi> yet thou art a <hi>Child of Wrath by Nature,</hi> thou haſt a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of iniquity that flows ſtill, to defile all that thou doſt, yea to pollute all the good Creatures of God that thou enjoyeſt. A Fountain is flowing continually: day and night it is venting its Waters, ſo out of the evil Treaſure of thy heart, thou art ſtill bringing forth evil things, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.35. <hi>Out of the heart proceeds evil thoughts, Murthers, Adulteries, and many more evils,</hi> Mat. 25.19. and ſhall the guilt of all, the burthen of all reſt upon thee? wilt thou keep thy filthy Garments, and retain thy ſpots and ſtains? will they not then render thee loathſome, and abominable: is the Fountain ſo near, and wilt thou not have recourſe to it, and make uſe of it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Take heed that thou doſt ſet up any in oppoſition to, or Competition with this Fountain. Do not put thy penitential Tears or Reformation in the place of the Blood of Chriſt. <hi>God hath eſtabliſhed the Sacrifice of Chriſt,</hi> Heb. 10.9. This is the only Merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious cauſe of Juſtification, and means of atonement; beware therefore that thou doſt not miſtake and tread in the ſteps of the blind zealous <hi>Jews,</hi> that went about to eſtabliſh their own Righteouſneſs, and did not ſubmit to the righteouſneſs of God.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93518:16"/>Here was mans eſtabliſhment directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Gods Eſtabliſhment, as if they muſt build a proud <hi>Babel</hi> of their own to get up to Heaven by, when God had provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Jeſus the Mediator as a long compleat ſpiritual Ladder for men to aſcend to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by, it is the greateſt curſe not to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Righteouſneſs of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.27. this is a horrid Imprecation on the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Jews, Let them not come into thy Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs;</hi> and wilt thou bring this curſe on thy own Soul. <hi>He that come into Gods Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, ſhall never come into Condemnation,</hi> Joh. 5.24. It is by Faith alone that we come into, and are Intereſted in this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>The Righteouſneſs of God is revealed from Faith to Faith,</hi> Rom. 1.17. Faith begins to apprehend, goes on to apply this Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and at laſt doth terminate, center and reſt in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I would put you in remembrance of the great Phyſician of Souls, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Mat. 9.12, 13. <hi>Never was there Phyſician like to him,</hi> he firſt died himſelf to provide a ſoveraign Remedy, and then viſits the dead and applys it to them. You are ſenſible of bodily Diſeaſes, you complain of them, you groan under them, yet they do but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Soul and Body, but will you not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and be affected with your ſpiritual Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies, which will part God and their Souls
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93518:16"/>for ever. To all other Diſeaſes, Sinners add a Lethargy, they are ſtupid, ſenſeleſs of their Miſery and danger. Though the world be full of ſick Folks, yet how little practice hath the great Phyſician? How few apply themſelves as Patients to him, or ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly commit their ſick dying Souls to him to be recovered by him; Is the <hi>Fall of Adam</hi> and the ſin and corruption of the world that floweth from it, but a Fiction or Fable, that you have no ſenſe or feeling of theſe things? will you ſay you are not ſiek or diſeaſed till you ſuddenly drop down to Hell? Are you reſolved to continue and dye in your ſins? What an aggravation will this be of your wilful obſtinacy, that you will periſh when the Phyſician is ſo near, and the remedy is at hand.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I would put y ou in remembrance of a great Supper, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.16. of an <hi>excellent Feaſt</hi> that God hath provided, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.6 and hath invited you to. God the Father gives you the true bread from Heaven, <hi>John</hi> 6.32. There wants nothing to your participation of it but a due Eſteem, and thankful accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of it. This is an excellent Supper, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Fire on an Altar, Heb.</hi> 13.10. and <hi>Feaſt on a Sacrifice offered by the Son of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7, 8. The Lord's gracious Call, if you echo to it; his free Invitation, if you comply with it gives you a right to all this ſpiritual good
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93518:17"/>cheer; tho you are <hi>poor, maimed, halt,</hi> and <hi>blind,</hi> yet all your Defects ſhall be paſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, none of them ſhall exclude you from the <hi>Feaſt, Luke</hi> 14.21 God is ſo ſet upon fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his <hi>Houſe with Gueſts, Luke</hi> 14.23. that he hath commanded us to compel you to <hi>come in.</hi> This is <hi>ſtrange Averſneſs, Corruption and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> in poor and Famiſhing ſinuers, that they need to be compelled to come in to a <hi>Feaſt,</hi> and this is wonderful goodneſs in <hi>God,</hi> that he chargeth us to <hi>compel you,</hi> both by remonſtrating your ſin and danger, if you do not come, and by repreſenting to you the <hi>Excellency, Riches, and Grace of Jeſus Chriſt, to invite and allure you to come</hi> On do not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh your Souls by neglecting to feed on Chriſt, do not poyſon your ſouls by drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>the pleaſures of ſin that are but for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> O that we could ſo preſs theſe things on you, and that with ſuch warm hearts, and lively affections, that our importunity might anſwer our Commiſſions, and ſavour of a kind of Violence and Compulſion.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I wovld put you in remembrance of a <hi>ſpiritual Market</hi> that the Lord himſelf hath ſet up, and keeps. O improve this <hi>spiritual Market day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is food brought from far, that is not of the growth of this world; there is bread of God that cometh down from <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and giveth life to the world, John</hi> 6.33. the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93518:17"/>bread is <hi>living bread, John</hi> 6.51. and therefore well may it be <hi>bread of life, John</hi> 6.48.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Jeſus Chriſt imports <hi>spiritual food</hi> by the <hi>precious River,</hi> or <hi>Red Sea of his own blood.</hi> If there were not ſuch a <hi>Red Sea,</hi> there would be <hi>no Traffick or Commerce</hi> between <hi>Heaven and Earth.</hi> Chriſt is a <hi>Priest of good things, Heb.</hi> 9.11.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Jeſus Chriſt keeps a Market for the Poor, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. he encourages thoſe to trade with him that can <hi>bring neither mony nor price.</hi> If there were a Market kept in a City for the poor, how would all flock to it? And will you not that are <hi>spiritually poor, come and buy of Chriſt without Money or Price?</hi> It was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of <hi>Attica,</hi> that it was one of the pooreſt, moſt hungry, and barren Soil in <hi>Greece,</hi> and that therefore the Inhabſtants of it were moſt given to Trade and Merchandize. So your <hi>poverty</hi> ſhould preſs you to deal with Jeſus Chriſt, that is ſo liberal and free to thoſe that come to him, and will traffick with him; He requires you to part with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that will impoveriſh you or inrich him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You are undone for ever, if you buy not of Jeſus Chriſt, and obtain not his <hi>goods;</hi> your Eyes will be blind, if not anointed with his <hi>Eye-Salve;</hi> your Souls will be naked, if not cloathed with his <hi>white Raiment;</hi> your Spirits will be poor to Eternity, if you buy not his <hi>Gold tried in the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93518:18"/>
            <p n="5">5. I would put you in remembrance of your work in God's Vineyard, that you are hired to mind and proſecute, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.1, 2. <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven is like to an Houſehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that went forth to hire Labourers into his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</hi> You cannot pretend, or excuſe your ſelves as the Heathen World, and ſay, <hi>None hath hired you,</hi> and therefore you ſtand idle, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.6. <hi>God</hi> hath come forth ſeveral times in the day of your life to hire you. Tho Miniſters have a larger Vineyard to culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, yet every particular Chriſtian hath a leſſer piece of Ground to manure, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his labours on; You have your own Hearts to keep, your own Families to watch over, your Neighbours to have on Eye to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to inſtruct, exhort, warn, reprove, as opportunity is offered, or Neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires. The work that God calls you to is great; you muſt prune, weed, water, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove your Vineyard; The work is No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Honourable, to render your own Souls and the Souls of others, fruitful Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards to God, to yeild ſuch Wine as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in, as will cheer the heart of Chriſt, and of Saints; The work is profitable; you will record in Heaven what you do on Earth for his glory; by your diligence and faithfulneſs <hi>Fruit will be brought forth, that will abound to your account in the great day of the Lord,</hi> Phil. 4.17. Suffer not therefore <hi>your Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:93518:18"/>to be over-run with Nettles, Briars or Thorns, or to lie open and unfenced.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I would mind you of your <hi>Race, Heb.</hi> 12.1, 2. as there is <hi>Hope ſet before you, Heb.</hi> 6.18. ſo there is <hi>a Race ſet before you, Heb.</hi> 12.1. Keep your eye ſtedy on the Mark, and bend your courſe directly towards it. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>I follow on, I preſs forward in a ſtrait line, towards the mark,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.26. I do not ſometimes move one way, ſometimes another; this would be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to run as if we were uncertain what courſe to ſteer, what mark to aim at, what Prize to run for. He that is a double-minded man, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues Two Objects, doth run ſo obſcurely, ſometimes inclining to one Object, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time following another, as if he were uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain which is the beſt Maſter, which is the <hi>chief Good.</hi> Again, perſons may be ſaid to run as <hi>uncertain,</hi> or not to <hi>run with any Evidence,</hi> when they make no viſible progreſs, when they do not get ground, and advance in the way everlaſting. Perſons run <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>darkly,</hi> when they do not manifeſt any proficiency in the Knowledge and Grace of Chriſt, when they neither root deeply in him, or manifeſtly grow up into him, 2 <hi>Col.</hi> 6.7. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15. look to it that you not only hold out as <hi>Travellers,</hi> but alſo that you may haſt as <hi>Racers;</hi> as you are to beware of <hi>wrong ſteps</hi> out of the way, ſo alſo of <hi>ſlow ſteps</hi> in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93518:19"/>it; the mark is <hi>perfect Holineſs,</hi> the prize is <hi>glorious Happineſs;</hi> there is an <hi>excellency</hi> in the Mark, as well as in the Prize, yea, the very Mark here may be accounted a Prize; we profit and advantage our ſelves when we have our fruit to Holineſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22. O! therefore forget what <hi>is behind,</hi> and reach forth to what <hi>is before, Phil.</hi> 3.13, 14. let not any attainments in <hi>Grace</hi> ſlacken your pace, cool your Zeal, abate your diligence or fervency; but be as earneſt, as if you had but juſt now ſtarted, or were taking your firſt ſteps in the Spiritual Race; this is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to forget what is behind, tho the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Inheritance be properly a <hi>Legacy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed in Chriſts Teſtament,</hi> Heb. 9.15. yet the <hi>Lord</hi> to encourage, and honour our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and to reward our obedience, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth it as a Prize to be won by us, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14. tho we live, move and act by the <hi>ſtrength</hi> and influence of Grace continually.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Let me put you in remembrance of your Account; <hi>we muſt all stand before the Judgment ſeat of Christ, and every one of us muſt give an account of himſelf to God,</hi> Rom. 14.10, 12. the account is long and large, there are innumerable thoughts, words, actions, to be accounted for; there are Regiſters, and Records of all kept above, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.6. behold it is written before me, <hi>God would not have been a Lawgiver, if he deſign'd alſo to be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93518:19"/>a Judg:</hi> The Divine Records muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> viewed, the Books muſt be opened, the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of Sinners ſtated, and the Sentence paſs on them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. Our Lord will come and reckon with his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <hi>and ſummon Stewards to give an account of their Stewardſhips,</hi> Luke 16.1, 2. O! there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let not your Lords Stock, Talents, or Pounds lye idle, and dead in your hands; as one Candle will tind or light a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Candles, ſo let that knowledg you have received, be improved to enlighten many others; let the Love of Chriſt ſo burn in your Hearts, ſo flame out in your words, and Actions, that all thoſe may be heated that come near to you, or Converſe with you; let your Loins be girt, work ſtrenuouſly, and diligently; let your <hi>Lamps be burning,</hi> act wiſely, and skilfully, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.35. yet when you have done all, <hi>confeſs your ſelves to be unprofitable Servants,</hi> that you have not merited, that any reward or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit ſhould redound to you from ſuch ſick Service, from ſuch defective and imperfect Obedience. Lay all your Offerings on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as an <hi>Altar;</hi> let all your ſins be drowned, and your Service waſhed in Chriſt's Blood, how elſe can you account with God for Years, Months, or one Day; the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly return to take an account, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.12. He is <hi>the Nobleman that is gone into a far Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93518:20"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> receive a Kingdom, and return;</hi> and ſhortly your Spirits muſt return to God, to give an account, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.7. All you have done will follow, overtake, meet you in another <hi>world,</hi> Think on, prepart for your account; ſet this Sentence on the Head of your account, <hi>The Blood of Jeſus Christ, the Son of God, cleanſeth from all ſin,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. then this paſſage may be put at the Foot of it, <hi>There is no condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
            <p>I have done with the Text of Scripture that I pitched on, and I ſhall now proceed to ſpeak ſomething on that Text of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that the Lord hath choſen to be the Occaſion of this mournful ſolemnity.</p>
            <p>Two things I would propoſe to you on this Occaſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. O conſider of, reflect upon, and be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected with this ſad, ſudden, and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſtroke of Providence: ſhould not this make deep impreſſions on your hearts, that a faithful and skillful Labourer is in the midſt of his days diſcharged from his <hi>work,</hi> when a great <hi>Door</hi> is open for Service, and <hi>the Fields are white to the Harvest;</hi> when the Neceſſities of Souls are ſo great, and <hi>the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers are ſo few</hi> to attend them Pauſe, and ſtay your thoughts on this ſad diſpenſation; a Star is taken down from the Orb, and Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament of the Church, a Lamp of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uary is put out, a Shepherd is removed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93518:20"/>from his <hi>Flock,</hi> an Amba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>dor of Peace is recalled by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>King of Glory.</hi> It is true, the <hi>hand of the Lord hath done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> but may not your ſins have been the meritorious and procuring cauſe of it? have not many of you heard the Word from him with drouſie Ears, cold Hearts uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned Spirits! have you not made light of the Travel of Chriſt's ſoul, of the purchaſe of his blood, of the Legacies of his <hi>Teſtament?</hi> have not your hearts been frozen with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, tho with reſpect to the warm diſpenſation of the Goſpel among you, you have liv'd in the <hi>Torrid Zone</hi> of Love? have not ſome of you drawn out the Fatal Web of your iniquity, even under his Miniſtry, and ſo provoked God to cut ſhort the precious thread of his Life? and have not the looſeneſs of ſome, and the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs and unthankfulneſs of others, ſnatch'd your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor away out of the World, ſilenc'd and laid him in the duſt? have not your Ears and Hearts been ſtopt from hearing the word, and ſo you have provoked God to ſhut his mouth from Preaching it any more among you? do not ſooth, or flatter your ſelves, this is a loud ſpeaking reproving, rebuking Providence to you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. O! cry earneſtly and fervently to God to ſupply your wants, and to fill up this breach; plead with the great Shepherd to raiſe you up a Paſtor according to his own heart, to feed the flock of God among you, with knowledg and underſtanding, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.15. it is a great work skilfully to feed the Flock of God, rightly to divide the word of truth, and to give every one his Portion, terror to ſinners, comfort to ſaints, inſtructions and exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to both, pray to the Lord of the Harveſt to provide you a Labourer, Matt. 9. <hi>laſt.</hi> ſo great are the diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements to this ſacred Function from an ungrateful World, that the <hi>Lord of the Harvest muſt thrust forth La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers,</hi> Matt. 9. <hi>laſt.</hi> And ſo great is the <hi>Carnality,</hi> and averſeneſs of People from the Feaſt of Jeſus Chriſt, that Miniſters muſt compel gueſts to come in; it is the <hi>Lord of the Harveſt</hi> that muſt fit and furniſh men to be Labourers; it is he that muſt enrich them with Grace, and fill them with the Spirit: It is ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:93518:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that become an Exalted Glorified <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> beſtow on the Church, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10, 11. <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> take them in his own Net as Fiſh, and then fit them to be Fiſhermen; he muſt firſt gather them into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> own Fold as Sheep, and then render them meet to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Shepherds; he muſt firſt eſpouſe them to himſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then Enlighten their Minds, and inflame their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to Wooe others for himſelf; he that hath not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Embraced Chriſt's Offers, and conſented to match <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him, will but coldly Proſecute Chriſts Suit, to gain others to the Lord of Glory. In the judgment of a learned man,
<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>leet</hi> in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Irenicum.</hi>
               </note> Miniſters, Paſtors and Teachers are called Saints, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which he thus renders, For the perfecting, or fitting of the Saints for the work of the Miniſtry; that is, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ing or fitting of Miniſters, that are, or ſhould be Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry. As the Prieſts <hi>Court</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Temple, by ſome ſteps higher than the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Court,</hi> ſo Chriſt's Miniſters ſhould be higher, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> above the People, both in Knowledge, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: Be earneſt Solicitors to the Father of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>, that he would not leave you deſolate, as <hi>ſheep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> ſhepherd;</hi> as in ſome Games among the <hi>Grecians,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> did run carrying a burning Lamp, and then deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>'d it to another to run alſo with it; ſo this Servant of the Lord how deceaſed, did in his Life-time run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> you, carrying the ſacred Lamp of the Goſpel. O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to God to raiſe up another to take his Lamp, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it further before you, to direct your hearts into the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God, and to guide your Feet in the way of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93518:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
